Iran, however, still has another card to
play. On July 20th, Yemen's Houthis
announced the start of a naval blockade
of Saudi Arabia. They warned that
vessels calling at Saudi ports or
carrying cargo to or from them could be
attacked anywhere. Although the blockade
announced by the Houthis, at least in
theory, applies only to Saudi Arabia
rather than to the closure of the Bap
Alandab Strait itself. That distinction
matters far less to shipping companies
and insurers. After the war in Gaza
began, the Houthis launch [music]
attacks on commercial vessels linked to
Israel in solidarity with Hamas. In
practice, their campaign effectively
closed Bab Almandab Straight between
2023 and 2025 and forced the world's
largest shipping companies to avoid the
Red Sea and take the much longer route
around Africa.